Guide to the Chinese Gaming Counters Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Gaming Counters with Identified or Attributed Provenance, circa 1700-circa 1840; Series I; 182
  - Richmond alias Webb family, Stewkley, Buckinghamshire, and Rodbourne Cheney in Swindon, Wiltshire, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and a crest of a tilting spear broken in three parts, one piece erect, the other two in saltire, enfiled with a ducal crown on a torse above an escutcheon with the monogram "C.", circa 1780-1790 (Box 1, Folder 141)
  - Richtie family
    - Round counter with a crest of a cubit arm holding a cross moline on a torse above a monogram "IR" and a scene with two insects., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 142)
      Verso of three Chinese men, one man carrying a staff, and a village scene.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a crest of a cubit arm holding a cross moline on a torse above a monogram "IR" and a scene with two dogs., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 143)
    - Rectangle counter with a crest of a cubit arm holding a cross moline on a torse above a monogram "IR" and a scene with a bird and an insect., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 144)
  - Robarts and Wilkinson family, London, England
    Probably the family of Abraham Wildey Robarts (1779-1858) and Charlotte Anne Wilkinson (1788-1865).
    - Oval counter with a drilled border and an escutcheon of quarterly first and fourth three crossbows and second and third a chevron between three martlets, impaling a fess counter vair between three unicorns, below a crest of a stag couchant regardant on a torse and helm. Both sides flanked by flowers., circa 1810 (Box 1, Folder 145)
      Verso of a Chinese man holding a staff.
  - Roberts, John (1739-1810)
    A director of the East India Company between 1764 to 1808.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and a crest of a paschal lamb passant, holding the banner on both sides., circa 1770 (Box 1, Folder 146)
    - Round counter with a line border and a crest of a paschal lamb passant, holding the banner on both sides., circa 1770 (Box 1, Folder 147)
  - Robertson family, Pitmillan, Aberdeenshire, Scotland
    - Round counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon with three wolves' heads erased in chief, in base a chaplet, and a bordure counter-componee below a crest of a hand from the wrist holding a dagger supporting the imperial crown and above the motto "Virtutis gloria merces" and flanked by a scene with two wolves., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 148)
      Verso of three Chinese men, one man riding an ass, and a village scene.
    - Rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon with three wolves' heads erased in chief, in base a chaplet, and a bordure counter-componee below a crest of a hand from the wrist holding a dagger supporting the imperial crown and above the motto "Virtutis gloria merces" and flanked by a scene with two wolves., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 149)
      Verso of three Chinese men, one man on a boat, and a village scene.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon with three wolves' heads erased in chief, in base a chaplet, and a bordure counter-componee below a crest of a hand from the wrist holding a dagger supporting the imperial crown and above the motto "Virtutis gloria merces" and flanked by a scene with two wolves., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 150)
  - Romerly family, attributed
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a lion's gamb on a torse above a monogram "R" and flanked by flowers., circa 1790-1840 (Box 1, Folder 151)
      Verso has a checkerboard pattern.
  - Ross family, Priesthill, Scotland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and an escutcheon with three lions rampant below a crest of a dexter hand holding a laurel wreath and above the motto "Nobilis est ira leonis.", circa 1770 (Box 1, Folder 152)
  - Rowe family, Windley Hill, Derbyshire, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a dexter hand holding a trefoil on a torse. Both sides flanked with flowers., circa 1790-1830 (Box 1, Folder 153)
      Verso has monogram "GMB."
  - Scrase family, Blatchington, Sussex, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with deep carving an a floral border and a crest of a falcon with wings addorsed proper, beaked, membered, and belled standing on the stock of a tree, round the last a snake on a torse under the motto "Volando repitilia sperno," and flanked by a scene with two Chinese men., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 154)
      Verso of two Chinese men, one man in a boat, and a village scene.
  - Seton family, Touch, Stirlingshire, Scotland
    Probably Lillian Seton (died 1835), wife of Henry Seton Steuart (1759–1836), 1st Baronet of Allanton.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon with quarterly, first and fourth, three crescents within a double tressure flory counterflory; second and third three escutcheons for Hat; behind the shield two spears in saltire, bearing on their points a royal helmet and shield of the arms of Scotland below a crest of a boar's head couped and supporters of two greyhounds proper above the motto forward ours and flanked by a scene with two Chinese men, one man preparing a chicken., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 155)
      Verso of two Chinese men and a village scene, flanked by a scene with two tigers.
  - Shore family of Derbyshire, England
    - Round counter with a line border and an escutcheon with a chevron between three bay leaves vertical and a crest of a stork reguardant and holding in the dexter foot a stone., circa 1730-1770 (Box 1, Folder 156)
      Verso has a stylized flower.
  - Smith and Cazalet family, Woodford, Essex, England
    Probably commemorating the marriage of Sarah Cazalet Smith (1762-1842) and William Smith (born circa 1762) in 1787.
    - Round counter with a Queen Charlotte border and an escutcheon with a lion passant guardant and a tower and anchor impaling a castle with two towers and a boar passant, circa 1790 (Box 1, Folder 157)
      Verso has a crest of a jester's head on a torse above a monogram "S."
  - Spens family, Edinburgh, Scotland.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with deep carving an a floral border and a crest of a hart's head erased proper below the motto "Si deus, quis contra" and flanked by a village scene., circa 1790 (Box 1, Folder 158)
  - Stewart and Lewys family, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a key fret border and an escutcheon with three owls in chief and an eagle displayed impaling a chevron between three trefoils slipped below a crest of an owl trussed, and flanked by a scene with a talbot and a scene with a bird., circa 1790-1840 (Box 1, Folder 159)
      Verso of three Chinese men; one man holds a sword and shield.
  - Stewart family, Earl of Galloway, Scotland
    Probably John Stewart (1736-1806), 7th Earl of Galloway.
    - Round counter with a Queen Charlotte border and an escutcheon with a fess chequy and surmounted of a bend within a tressure flory counterflory impaling three wolves' heads erased between six bars and below a crest of a pelican winged in her nest and feeding her young in a ducal crown, with supporters on dexter of a savage wreathed about the head and loins with laurel and holding a club over his dexter shoulder and on sinister a lion guardant, all above the motto "Vireseit vulnere virtus.", circa 1779 (Box 1, Folder 160)
      Verso has the crest of a pelican winged in her nest and feeding her young in a ducal crown above the monogram "G."
    - Rectangle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and an escutcheon with a fess chequy and surmounted of a bend within a tressure flory counterflory impaling three wolves' heads erased between six bars and below a crest of a pelican winged in her nest and feeding her young in a ducal crown, with supporters on dexter of a savage wreathed about the head and loins with laurel and holding a club over his dexter shoulder and on sinister a lion guardant, all above the motto "Vireseit vulnere virtus.", circa 1779 (Box 1, Folder 161)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and an escutcheon with a fess chequy and surmounted of a bend within a tressure flory counterflory impaling three wolves' heads erased between six bars and below a crest of a pelican winged in her nest and feeding her young in a ducal crown, with supporters on dexter of a savage wreathed about the head and loins with laurel and holding a club over his dexter shoulder and on sinister a lion guardant, all above the motto "Vireseit vulnere virtus.", circa 1779 (Box 1, Folder 162)
  - Stuart family, Isle of Bute, Scotland
    Probably James Archibald Stuart, later Stuart-Wortley-Mackenzie (1747-1818)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a geometric floral border and a crest of a unicorn's head armed and crined above an escutcheon with fess chequy., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 163)
      Verso has the monogram "JS."
    - Rectangle counter with a geometric floral border and a crest of a unicorn's head armed and crined above an escutcheon with fess chequy., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 164)
  - Stuart family, Lord Blantyre of Lanarkshire, Scotland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and an escutcheon with a fess chequy surmounted by a bend engrailed and in chief a rose, circa 1760 (Box 1, Folder 165)
      Probably Major-General Charles Stuart (circa 1758-1828), an officer in the East India Company Army and a member of the Supreme Council of Bengal.
      Verso has a crest of a dove with an olive leaf in its mouth and above monogram "CS." and below the motto, "Sola juvat virtus."
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and an escutcheon with a fess chequy surmounted by a bend engrailed and in chief a rose below a crest of a dove with an olive leaf in its mouth and above the initials "SJV" (for the motto "Sola juvat virtus"), circa 1760 (Box 1, Folder 166)
      Probably William Stuart (died 1776), 9th Lord Blantyre.
      Verso has a baron crown and monogram B.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and an escutcheon with a fess chequy surmounted by a bend engrailed and in chief a rose, circa 1760 (Box 1, Folder 167)
      Probably Alexander Stuart (died 1783), 10th Lord Blantyre.
      Verso has a monogram "S" and the motto, "Sola juvat virtus.'
  - Stylman family of Steeple Ashton, Wiltshire, England
    - Round counter with a line border and an escutcheon impaled: sinister a unicorn passant on a chief and three palets, dexter a chevron between three pierced mullets, as well as a crest a camel's head erased and biletee, muzzled, collared, lined, and ringed., circa 1700-1770 (Box 1, Folder 168)
    - Fish-shaped counter with a crest of a camel's head erased and biletee, muzzled, collared, lined, and ringed on a torse., circa 1720-1760 (Box 1, Folder 169)
  - Townshend family, Raynham Hall, Norfolk, England
    Probably Anne Montgomery Townshend (circa 1752-1819), wife of George Townshend (1724-1807), 1st Marquess Townshend.
    - Shuttle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a marquess crown above monogram "AT" and flanked by flowers on both sides., circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 170)
  - Turner and Wolmer families
    Probably the family of John Woolmore (1755-1837), a ship captain and shareholder in the East India Company, and his second wife, Harriet Turner Woolmore (died 1845).
    - Shuttle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and an escutcheon with ermine pierced with four fers-de-moline impaling a chevron between three escallops below a crest of two lobster claws holding an escallop., circa 1790 (Box 1, Folder 171)
  - Watts family, Hanslope, Buckinghamshire, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and a crest of a greyhound sejant supporting with the dexter foot an arrow., circa 1750-1770 (Box 1, Folder 172)
      Verso has an unusual pattern.
  - White family, Poole and Tickleford, Dorset, as well as Yeovil, Somerset, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and a crest of an arm embowed holding in a hand a stork by the legs, wings expanded proper on a torse., circa 1780-1790 (Box 1, Folder 173)
      Verso has diapering and the monogram "W."
  - Willard and Thomas family
    - Round counter with a double-drilled border and an escutcheon of Willard (a chevron between three jars) quartering Davies (three roundels in chief above a lion rampant) on impaling Thomas (chevron between three Cornish choughs) above motto "In domino confido.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 174)
      Verso has two crests: a griffin's head couped on a torse and a demi-mouse rampant regardant on a torse.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a double-drilled border and an escutcheon of Willard (a chevron between three jars) quartering Davies (three roundels in chief above a lion rampant) on impaling Thomas (chevron between three Cornish choughs) above motto "In domino confido.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 175)
    - Rectangle counter with a double-drilled border and an escutcheon of Willard (a chevron between three jars) quartering Davies (three roundels in chief above a lion rampant) on impaling Thomas (chevron between three Cornish choughs) above motto "In domino confido.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 176)
  - Wood family, Ottershaw, Surrey, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a reserves border and an escutcheon with a oak tree eradicated below a crest of a ship under sail and the motto "Tutus in undis.", circa 1760 (Box 1, Folder 177)
  - Worshipful Company of Vintners, London, England
    The Worshipful Company of Vintners is one of the Livery Companies of the City of London, England.
    - Fish-shaped counter with scales and an escutcheon with a chevron between three tuns., circa 1720-1760 (Box 1, Folder 178)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with an escutcheon with a chevron between three tuns., circa 1730-1770 (Box 1, Folder 179)
- Gaming Counters with Unidentified Provenance, circa 1700-circa 1840; Series II; (124 items)
  Arranged into six subseries based on inscriptions: Heraldic Escutcheon and Motto; Heraldic Escutcheon and Monogram; Heraldic Escutcheon; Monogram and Crest; Crest Only; and Monogram Only
  Gaming counters with unidentified or unattributed provenance.
  - Heraldic Escutcheon and Motto
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and an escutcheon with three crescents and a crescent of a dragon statant, spouting fire, proper on a ducal crown, below the motto, "Hazard zet Fordward.", circa 1750-1770 (Box 1, Folder 180)
      Verso has a rose.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a key fret border and an escutcheon of a monk holding a cane and bag under a crest of a cross suspended from an arm on a torse and above the motto "In cruce glorior.", circa 1790-1840 (Box 1, Folder 181)
      Verso of two Chinese men and a village.
    - Round counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a talbot collared, chained, and sejant on a torse below the motto "Dum spiro spero," and flanked by a scene with two moths., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 182)
      Verso of three Chinese women and a village scene.
    - Round counter with a drilled border and a crest of a stag trippant surrounded by motto "Do right and fear not.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 183)
      Verso of a Chinese man seated and holding a drum.
    - Rectangle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a stag trippant surrounded by motto "Do right and fear not.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 184)
      Verso of a Chinese man holding a bundle.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a stag trippant surrounded by motto "Do right and fear not.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 185)
      Verso of a Chinese man holding a dagger.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with deep carving an a floral border and a crest of a dexter cubit arm holding a sword below the motto "Pro patria" and flanked by a village scene with a bird and dog., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 186)
  - Heraldic Escutcheon and Monogram
    Arranged alphabetically by monogram.
    - Monogram "FCM"
      - Oblong rectangle counter with a fretted border and an escutcheon a lion rampant and holding a sun between its paws below a crest of a leopard's head and neck couped on a torse., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 187)
        Verso of a monogram "FCM."
        Both sides flanked by a scene with two Chinese men.
    - Monogram "RFD"
      - Shuttle counter with a drilled border and an escutcheon with a chevron with three roundels between three pheons below a crest of an armored dexter arm embowed and holding an arrow on a torse and flanked by flowers., circa 1780-1800 (Box 1, Folder 188)
        Verso has a crest of an armored dexter arm embowed and holding an arrow on a torse above the monogram "RFD" and diapering.
      - Oval counter with a drilled border and an escutcheon with a chevron with three roundels between three pheons below a crest of an armored dexter arm embowed and holding an arrow on a torse and flanked by flowers., circa 1780-1800 (Box 1, Folder 189)
    - Monogram "WS"
      - Shuttle counter with a drilled border and an escutcheon with a monogram "WS" and flanked by flowers., circa 1780-1810 (Box 1, Folder 190)
  - Heraldic Escutcheon
    - Oblong rectangle counter with canted corners and a line border, as well as an escutcheon with a tower below a ducal crown., circa 1730-1770 (Box 1, Folder 191)
      Probably a counter for a French family.
    - Round counter with a line border and an escutcheon with three foxes impaling three horseshoes, below an earl crown., circa 1730-1740 (Box 1, Folder 192)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and an escutcheon with a trident on a bend combined with fleur de lis surrounded by three acorns below a ducal crown., circa 1730-1770 (Box 1, Folder 193)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with an escutcheon with a tree supported by two lions below an emblem of a coronet., circa 1730-1770 (Box 1, Folder 194)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a floral border and an escutcheon of a chevron below a annulet (small ring) and below a tree on a torse., circa 1750-1780 (Box 1, Folder 195)
      Verso has a scene of two lovebirds on a torse.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and an escutcheon with a per bend between two thistles below a ducal crown., circa 1760-1770 (Box 1, Folder 196)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and an escutcheon of two axes and a crescent combined with three swans and a small escutcheon below a ducal crown., circa 1760-1770 (Box 1, Folder 197)
      Verso has a floral pattern and moths.
    - Shuttle counter with a drilled border and an escutcheon with three stags' heads erased below a crest of a lion rampant and in its paws holding a ball on a torse and flanked by flowers, circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 198)
    - Round counter with a geometric border and an escutcheon of a chevron between three bucks trippant under a crest of a stag's head erased on a torse., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 199)
      Verso of a Chinese man wading in a river.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon of a with a per fess and three axes in chief below a crest of a stag courant and regardant., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 200)
      Verso of a Chinese man with a cylindrical container and buildings.
  - Monogram and Crest
    - Monogram "AG" and Crest of an Eagle
      - Round counter with a Queen Charlotte border and a crest of an eagle with its wings displayed and elevated on a torse above the monogram "AG.", circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 201)
        Verso has a Chinese man carrying a yoke.
      - Round counter with a Queen Charlotte border and a crest of an eagle with its wings displayed and elevated on a torse above the monogram "AG.", circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 202)
        Verso has a Chinese man carrying a tea tray upon his head.
    - Monogram "B" and a Crest of an Armored Dexter Arm
      - Shuttle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and a crest of an armored dexter arm embowed and holding in its hand a dagger on a torse above the monogram "B.", circa 1780-1790 (Box 1, Folder 203)
        "Verso has diapering and the figure "5."
    - Monogram "C" and a Crest of a Fleur-de-lis
      - Round counter with a drilled border and a fleur-de-lis above a monogram "C.", circa 1790-1830 (Box 1, Folder 204)
        Verso of a Chinese man blowing a horn.
    - Monogram "C" and a Crest of a Leopard Passant
      - Oval counter with a Queen Charlotte border and a crest of a leopard passant gardant on a torse above an escutcheon with the monogram "C.", circa 1780-1810 (Box 1, Folder 205)
      - Oblong rectangle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and a crest of a leopard passant gardant on a torse above an escutcheon with the monogram "C.", circa 1780-1810 (Box 1, Folder 206)
      - Round counter with a Queen Charlotte border and a crest of a leopard passant gardant on a torse above an escutcheon with the monogram "C.", circa 1780-1810 (Box 1, Folder 207)
    - Monogram "C" and a Crest of a Demi-Phoenix and Church Tower
      - Round counter with a geometric border and a crest of a demi-phoenix and church tower issuing from a viscount crown on a torse above a monogram "C.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 208)
      - Oblong rectangle counter with a geometric border and a crest of a demi-phoenix and church tower issuing from a viscount crown on a torse above a monogram "C.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 209)
      - Rectangle counter with a geometric border and a crest of a demi-phoenix and church tower issuing from a viscount crown on a torse above a monogram "C.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 210)
        Verso of a Chinese man sitting at a table.
    - Monogram "CAT" and a Crest of a Dexter Hand
      - Round counter with a fretted border and a crest of a dexter hand with a raised index finger and little finger., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 211)
        Verso of a monogram "CAT."
    - Monogram "CEMB" and a Crest of a Hawk
      - Rectangle counter with deep carving and a floral border and a crest of a hawk rising on a hawk's lure on a torse above a monogram "CEMB" and flanked by a scene with two crabs and a village., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 212)
        Verso of three Chinese men, two carrying tools, and a village scene.
      - Oblong rectangle counter with deep carving an a floral border and a crest of a hawk rising on a hawk's lure on a torse above a monogram "CEMB" and flanked by a scene of a village., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 213)
      - Round counter with deep carving an a floral border and a crest of a hawk rising on a hawk's lure on a torse above a monogram "CEMB" and flanked by a scene with a bird and a village., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 214)
        Verso of three Chinese women and a village scene, including a tall pagoda.
    - Monogram "CWM" and a Crest of a Talbot
      - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a talbot passant on a torse and flanked by a scene with two birds., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 215)
        Verso of a monogram "CWM" franked by two Chinese men and a village scene.
    - Monogram "FHM" and a Crest of a Lion's Head
      - Round counter with a drilled border and a crest of a lion's head and neck erased on a torse above the monogram "FHM" and flanked by flowers on both sides., circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 216)
      - Shuttle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a lion's head and neck erased on a torse above the monogram "FHM" and flanked by flowers on both sides., circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 217)